I Tell You, It’s True

by Poul Anderson

Poul Anderson sold his first science fiction story in 1944 and has not looked back since. He is almost a prototype of the ideal science fiction writer with a degree in physics to back up a masterful story telling technique—plus an enviable capacity for food and beer as well as the ability to speak Danish. Some of his stories are light entertainment. Others are grimly complete in their examination of the possibilities of a technological innovation, and this is one of them.

The mansion stood on the edge of Ban Pua town, hard by the Nan River. Through a door open to its shady-side verandah, you saw slow brown waters and intensely green trees beyond that flickered in furnace sunlight. Somewhere monkeys chattered. A couple of men in shabby uniforms stoically kept watch. Their rifles looked too big for them. George Rainsdon wondered if they had personally been in combat against his countrymen.

He brought his attention back to the interior. Now, he thought. The sweat that plastered his shirt to him felt suddenly cold. Yet this room, stripped of the luxuries that the landlord owner had kept, was almost serene in its austerity. The four Thais across the table were much more at ease than the five Americans.

Rainsdon knew what implacability underlay those slight, polite smiles. Behind Chukkri hung portraits of Lenin and Ho Chi Minh.

Attendants brought tea and small cakes.

Rainsdon made a sitting bow. “Again I thank Your Excellency for agreeing to receive our delegation,” he said with the fluency that years as a diplomat in Bangkok had given him. “Believe me, sir, the last thing my government wishes is a repetition of the Vietnam tragedy. We desire no involvement in the conflict here except to act as peacemakers.” He laid on the table the box he was carrying. “In token, we beg that you accept this emblem of friendship.”

“I thank you,” the leader of the Sacred Liberation Movement answered. “The solution of your difficulty is quite simple. You need merely withdraw your military personnel. But let us see the gift you graciously bring.”

He opened the package and took forth a handsome bronze statuette in an abstract native-derived style. Its plaque held soft words. One of his generals frowned. Chukkri flashed him a sardonic glance that might as well have said aloud, Not even the Americans are stupid enough to imagine that assassinating us will halt the advance of our heroic troops. “Please thank your President on my behalf,” he uttered.

The warmth of his touch completed the activation of a circuit.

Rainsdon leaned forward. Go for broke! His slight giddiness passed into a feeling that resembled his emotions when he had led infantry charges in Korea in his long passed youth. The rehearsed but wholly sincere words torrented from him:

“Your Excellency. Gentlemen. Let me deliver, at this private and informal conference, the plain words of the United States Government. The United States has no aggressive intentions toward the people of Thailand or any other country. Our sole desire is to help Thailand end the civil war on terms satisfactory to everyone. The first and most essential prerequisite for peace is that your organization accept a cease-fire and negotiate in good faith with the legitimate government to arrange a plebiscite. Your ideology is alien to the Thai people and must not be forced on them. However, you will be free to advocate it, to persuade by precept and example, to offer candidates for office. If defeated, they must accept with grace; if victorious, they must work within the existing system. But we do not want you to renounce your principles publicly. If nothing else, you can be valuable intermediaries between us and capitals like Hanoi and Peking. Thereby you will truly serve the cause of peace and the liberation of the people.”

They sat still, the short, neat Asian men, for a time that grew and grew. Rainsdon’s back ached from tension. Would it work? Could it? How could it? He had said nothing they hadn’t heard a thousand times before and scorned as mendacious where it was not meaningless. They had fought, they had lost friends dear to them, they were ready to be slain themselves or to fight on for a weary lifetime; their cause was as holy to them as that of Godfrey of Bouillon had been to him—though it was no mere Jerusalem they would rescue from the infidel, it was mankind.

Finally, frowning, a fist clenched beside his untasted cup of tea,

Chukkri said, very low and slow: “I had not considered the matter in just those terms before. Would you explain in more detail?” Rainsdon heard a gasp from his aides. They had not expected their journey would prove anything except a barren gesture. Glory mounted in him. It does work! By God, it works!

He got busy. The circuitry in the statuette would fuse itself into slag after three hours. That ought to be ample time. The CIA had planned this operation with ultimate care.

The laboratories stood on the peninsula south of San Francisco, commanding a magnificent view of ocean if it were possible to overlook the freeway, the motels, and the human clutter on the beach. The sanctum where Edward Sigerist and Manuel Duarte had brought their guests made it easy to ignore such encroachments. The room, though big, was windowless; the single noise was a murmur of ventilators blowing air which carried a faint tinge of ozone; fluorescent panels threw cold light on the clutter of gadgetry burying the workbenches around the walls, and on the solitary table in the center where six men sat and regarded a thing.

Fenner from MIT spoke: “Pretty big for that level of output, isn’t it?” His tone was awed; he was merely breaking a lengthy silence.

“Breadboard circuit,” Sigerist answered, equally unnecessarily considering what a jumble of wires and electronic components the thing was. “Any engineer could miniaturize it to the size of your thumb, for short-range work, in a few months. Or scale it up for power, till three of them in synchronous satellites could blanket the Earth. If he couldn’t do that, from the cookbook, he’d better go back to chipping flints.” He was a large, shaggy, rumpled man. His voice was calm but his eyes were haunted.

“Of course, he’d need the specs,” said his collaborator, lean, intense, dark-complexioned Duarte. His glance ranged over the visitors. Fenner, physicist, sharp-featured beneath a cupola of forehead; Mot-tice, biochemist from London, plump and placid except for the sweat that now glistened on his cheeks; tiny Yuang of the Harvard psychology department; and Ginsberg of Cal Tech, who resembled any grocer or bookkeeper till you remembered his Nobel Prizes for quantum field theory and molecular biology. “That’s why we brought you gentlemen here.”

“Why the secrecy?” Yuang asked. “Our work has all been reported in the open literature. Others can build on it, as you have done. Others doubtless will.”

“N-n-not inevitably,” Sigerist replied. “Kind of a fluke, our success. This isn’t a big outfit, you know. Mostly we contract to do R and D on biomedical instrumentation. I’m alone in having a completely free hand, which is how come I get away with studying dowsing. I was carrying on Rocard’s investigations, which were published back in the mid-’60’s and never got the attention they deserved.” Receiving blank stares: “Essentially, he gave good theoretical and experimental grounds for supposing that dowsing results from the nervous system’s response to variations in terrestrial magnetism. I was using your data too, Dr. Mottice, Dr. Ginsberg. Then at the Triple-A-S meeting three years ago, I happened to meet Manuel at an afterhours beer party. He was with General Electric . . . He called to my notice the papers by Dr. Yuang and Dr. Fenner. We both took fire; I arranged for him to transfer here; we worked together. Kept our mouths shut, at first because we weren’t sure where we were going, later because we made a breakthrough and suddenly realized what it meant to the world.” He shrugged. “An unlikely set of coincidences, no?”

“Well,” Ginsberg inquired, “what effects do you anticipate?”

“For openers,” Duarte told him, “we can stop the war in Thailand. Soon after, we can stop all war everywhere.”

The room was long, mirrored, ornate in the red plush fashion of Franz Josef’s day. The handful of men who sat there were drab by contrast, like beetles.

Not a bad comparison, thought the President of the United States. For Party Secretary Tupilov, at least. Premier Grigorovitch seems a bit more human.

He made the slight, prearranged hand signal. His interpreter responded by nervously tugging his necktie. It energized a circuit in what appeared to be a cigarette case.

“First,” said the President, “I want to express my appreciation of your cooperativeness. I hope the considerable concessions made by the United States, especially with regard to the Southeast Asia question, seemed more than a bribe to win your presence here. I hope they indicated that my government genuinely desires a permanent settlement of the conflicts that rack the world—a settlement such that armed strife can never occur again.”

While his interpreter put it into Russian, he watched the two overlords. His heart thumped when Grigorovitch beamed and nodded. Tupilov’s dourness faded to puzzlement; he shook his big bald head as if to clear away an interior haze.

His political years had taught the President how to assume sternness at will, however more common geniality was. “I shall be blunt,” he continued. “I shall tell you certain home truths in unvarnished language. We can have no peace until every nation is secure. This requires general nuclear disarmament, enforced by adequate inspection. It requires that the great powers join to guarantee every country safety, not against overt invasion alone, but also against subversion and insurrection. Undeniably, every nation that we Americans label ‘free’ is not. Many of their governments are tyrannical and corrupt. But liberation is not to be accomplished through violent revolution on the part of fanatics who, if successful, would upset the world balance of power and so bring us to the verge of the final war.

“Instead, peace requires that the leading nations cooperate to make available to the people of every country the means for orderly replacement of their governments through genuinely free elections. This presupposes that they be granted freedom of speech, assembly, petition, travel, and worship, in fact as well as in name.

“Gentlemen, we have talked too long and done too little about democracy. We must begin by putting our own houses in order. You will not resent my stating that your house is in the most urgent need of this.”

For the only time on record, Igor Tupilov wept.

“I find it hard to believe,” Mottice whispered. “That fundamental a change . . . from a few radio quanta?”

“We found it hard to believe, too,” Sigerist admitted, grimly rather than excitedly. “However, your work on synergistics had suggested that the right combination of impulses might trigger autocatalytic transformations in the synapeses. It doesn’t take a lot, you see. These events happen on the molecular level. What’s needed is not quantity but quality: the exact frequencies, amplitudes, phases, and sequences.”

“Our initial evidence came from rats,” Duarte said. “When we could alter their training at will, we proceeded to monkeys, finally man. The human pattern turned out to be a good deal more complex, as you’d expect. Finding it was largely a matter of cut-and-try . . . and, again, sheer luck.”

Yuang scowled. “You still don’t know precisely what the chemistry and neurology are?”

“How could we, two of us in this short a time? Our inducer ought to make quite a research tool!”

“I am wondering about possible harm to the subject.”

“We haven’t found any,” Sigerist stated, “and we didn’t just use volunteers for experimentation, we took part ourselves. Nothing happens except that the subject believes absolutely what he’s told or what he reads while he’s in the inducer field. There doesn’t seem to be decay of the new patterns afterward. Why should there be? What we have is nothing but an instant re-educator.”

“Instant brainwasher,” Ginsberg muttered.

“Well, it’s subject to abuse, like all tools,” Fenner said. They could see enthusiasm rising in him. “Imagine, though, the potentialities for good. A scalpel can kill a man or save his life. Maybe the inducer can save his soul.”

The agent of the Human Relations Board smiled across his desk. “I think our meeting has a symbolic value beyond even what we hope to accomplish,” he said.

Hatred smoldered back at him from dark eyes under a bush of hair. One brown fist thumped a chair arm. The bearded lips spat: “Get with it, mother! I promised you an hour o’ my time for your donation to the Black Squadron, and sixty minutes by that clock is what you’re gonna get, mother.”

The local head of Citizens for Law and Order turned mushroom pallid. His dull-blue eyes popped behind their rimless glasses. “What?” he exclaimed. “You . . . gave government funds . . . to that gang of . . . of nihilists—?”

“You will recall, sir,” the Human Relations agent replied, mildly, “that you agreed to come after I promised that the investigation of the assault on Reverend Washington would be dropped.”

He pressed a button on his desk. “Ringing for coffee,” he said, repeating his smile. “I suspect we’ll be here longer than an hour.”

He leaned forward. As he spoke, passion transfigured his homely features. “Sirs,” he declared, “you are both men whose influence goes well beyond this community. Your power for good is potentially still greater than your power for evil. A moderate solution to the problems which called forth your respective organizations must be found . . . before the country we share is torn apart. It can be found! If not perfect satisfaction, then equal and endurable dissatisfaction. If not utopia, then human decency. The white man must lay aside his superiority complex, his greed, his indifference to the suffering around him. The black man must lay aside his hatred, his impatience, his unrealistic separatism. We must work and sacrifice together. We must individually strive to give more than we get, in order that our children may inherit what is rightfully theirs: freedom, equality, and well-being under the law. For we are in fact all equals, all Americans, all brothers in our common humanity.”

He spoke on, and his visitors looked from him to each other with a widening gaze, and at last, slowly, their hands reached forth to clasp.

“And if a mistake is made,” Duarte answered Fenner in a sarcastic tone, “why, you give the patient a jolt of inducer and straighten him out again.” He grinned. “Sig and I actually got to playing with that. He made me a Baptist. I retaliated by making him a vegetarian.”

“How’d it feel?” Yuang inquired, sharp-voiced.

“M-m-m . . . hard to describe.” Sigerist rubbed his chin and leaned back in his chair till he looked at the ceiling. “We knew what was going on, you see, which our test subjects didn’t. Nevertheless, vegetarianism seemed utterly right. No, let me rephrase that: it was right. I’d think of what I’ve read about slaughterhouses and—We foresaw this, naturally. We stuck by our promises to return next day and be, uh, disillusioned, told we’d been forced into a channel, that our prior beliefs and preferences were normal for us. I thought I could make the comparison later, having then experienced both attitudes, and decide objectively which was better. But right away, when Manuel spoke to me, after the slight initial fogginess of mind had cleared, right away I decided what the hell, I do like steak.”

Duarte sobered. “For my part,” he said, “frankly, I miss God. I’ve considered going back to religion. Might have done so by now, except I realize certain faiths are . . . well, easier to hold, and I’d be sensible to investigate first.”

Penny twisted a strand of blonde hair nervously between her fingers. Her bare foot kicked an old copy of the Tribe against a catbox ammoniacally overdue for changing, with a dry rustle and a small puff of Aug. Sunlight straggled through the window grime to glisten off bacon grease on the dishes which filled the sink in one comer of her pad. “Like, talk,” she invited. “Do your thing.”

“I hope you don’t consider me a busybody,” said the social worker in the enormous hat. She sighed. “You probably do. But with your unemployment compensation expiring—”

Penny sat down on the mattress which served for a bed, lit a cigarette, and wished it were a joint. “I’ll get along.”

The social worker raised a plump arm to point at Billy, playing contentedly with himself in his playpen. At eighteen months, his face had acquired enough individuality that Penny had felt sure Big Dick was the father. She often wondered where Big Dick had gone.

“I’m concerned about him,” the social worker proceeded. “Don’t you realize you’re creating a misfit?”

“This is a world he ought to fit into?” Penny drawled. “Come off it.” The smoke was pleasantly acrid in her nostrils.

“Do listen, darling.” The social worker gripped her big purse, almost convulsively, squeezing together the brass knobs on its clasp. “You’re throwing away his life as well as your own.”

For a moment the peace emblem drawn on the wall wobbled. Damn tobacco, Penny thought. Cancer. She stubbed out the cigarette on the floor. It occurred to her that she really must unplug the bathtub drain, or anyway wash her feet in the sink . . . Oddly hard to concentrate. The woman in the enormous hat droned on:

“—you’ll move in with yet another man, or he’ll move in with you. Don’t you realize that a kiss can transmit syphilis? You could infect your little boy.”

Oh, no! Horror struck. I never thought about that!

“—You say you are protesting the evil and corruption of society. What evil? What corruption? Look around you. Look at the Thailand Peace, the Vienna Detente, the Treaty of Peking. What about the steady decline of interracial violence, the steady growth of interracial cooperation? What about the new penological program, hundreds of prisoners let out of jail every day, going straight and staying straight?”

“Well,” Penny stammered, “well, uh, yeah, I guess that’s true, like I seen it in the papers, I guess, only can you trust the kept press?”

“Of course you can! Not that the press is kept. This is a free country. You have your own newspapers of dissent, don’t you?”

“Well, we got a lot to dissent about,” Penny said. The way the visitor talked and acted, she had to be a person who’d understand. “I don’t work on one myself, though. Like, that’s not my bag. I’m not the kind that wants to kill pigs or throw rocks, either. I mean, a pig’s human too, you know? Only when my friends keep getting busted or clubbed, like that, I can’t blame they get mad. See what I mean? If we could all love each other, the problems would go away. Only most people are so uptight they can’t love, they don’t know how, and the problems get worse and worse.” Penny shook her head, trying to clear out the haze. But things are getting better like she said! “Maybe they’ve finally begun to learn how in the establishment?”

“They have always known, my dear,” the social worker answered. “What they have found at last is practical ways to cure troubles. We have a wonderful future before us. And violence, dropping out, unfair criticism is not what’s bringing it. What we need is cooperation within the system.

“You’re not with it, Penny. I’ll tell you where it’s at. Law is where it’s at; the police aren’t your enemies, they’re your friends, your protectors. Cleanliness is where it’s at, health, leaving dope alone, regular habits, regular work; that’s how you contribute your share to the commune. And marriage. You simply don’t know what love is till you’re making it with one cat, the two of you sharing your whole lives, raising fine clean bright children in a country you are proud of—” I . . . I never saw . . . never understood . . .

Finally Penny cried on the large bosom, in the comforting circle of the plump arms. The social worker soothed her, murmured to her, breathed in her ear, “You don’t have to give up your friends, you know. On the contrary. Help them. Help me call them together for a rally where we can tell them—”

“What happens to the person who operates the inducer, hands out the propaganda?” Fenner wondered.

“Oh, the impulses can be screened off,” Sigerist replied. “You can easily imagine how. We used a grounded metal-mesh booth. Manuel’s since designed a screen in the form of a net over the head, which could be disguised by a wig or a hat. For weak short-range projections, anyhow. Powerful ones, meant to cover a large area, would doubtless continue to require a special room for the speaker.” He hesitated. “We haven’t established whether psychoinduction occurs with more than one type of radio input. If it does, perhaps a shield against a given type can be bypassed by another.”

“I tried to lie, experimentally, while under the field myself,” Duarte said. “And I couldn’t. I’d try to convince a volunteer that, oh, that two and two equals five. Right off, I’d get appalled and think, ‘You can’t do that to him! It isn’t a fact!’ Of course, fiction or poetry or something like that was okay to read aloud, except I got some odd looks from our subjects when I kept explaining at length that what they were hearing was untrue.”

“So we’d either speak our lies from the booth,” Sigerist put in, “or we’d tell them things we knew . . . believed . . . were real. That’s another funny experience. Reinforcement in the brain, I suppose. At any rate, you grow quite vehement, about everything from Maxwell’s equations on up. We confined ourselves to that sort of thing with the volunteers, understand. First, we’d no right to tamper with their minds. Second, we didn’t want to give the game away. They were always told this was a study of how the tracings on a new kind of three-dimensional EEG correlate with verbal stimuli. Our falsehoods were neutral items. ‘Have you heard Doc Malanowicz is trying to use the Hilsch tube in respiratory function measurements?’ Next day we’d disabuse them, always in such a fashion that they didn’t suspect. We hope. The spectacular lies we saved for each other.” His chuckle was not too happy a sound. “I’m a Republican and Manuel’s a Democrat. When we were experimenting, both of us under the inducer field—the temptation to make a convert grew almighty strong.”

“Ladies and gentlemen, the President of the United States.”

“My fellow Americans. Tonight I wish to discuss with you the state of the nation and of the world. Our problems are many and grave. You know them both by name and by experience—international turmoil; cruel ideologies; subversion; outright treason; lawlessness; domestic discord, worsened by the unfair criticism of certain so-called intellectuals—a small minority, I hasten to add, since by and large the intellectual community is firmly loyal to the American ideal.

“What is that ideal? Let me tell you the eternal truths on which this country is founded, for which it stands. We believe in God. We believe in country; we stand ready to fight and die if need be, in the conviction that America’s cause is always just. We believe in the democratic process, and therefore in the leaders which that process has given us—”

Ginsberg whistled. “If this gadget fell into the wrong hands—Help!”

“Would it necessarily?” Fenner asked. His glance flickered around the table. “I know what you’re thinking,” he said in a hurried voice. “ ‘The H-bomb’s not in a class with this.’ Right? Well, let me remind you that thermonuclear fusion is on the point of giving us unlimited power . . . clean power, that doesn’t poison air or soil. Let me remind you of lives saved and knowledge gained through abundant radionuclides. And the big birds haven’t flown yet, have they?” He drew breath. “If this, uh, inducer is as advertised, and I see no reason to doubt that, why, can’t you see what it’ll mean? Research. Therapy. Yes, and securing the world. I don’t mind admitting I’d turn it on some of those characters who’re destroying the ecology that keeps us all alive. Why not? Why can’t the inducer be used judiciously?”

“One problem is, when you have the specs, this is an easy thing to build, at least on a small scale,” Sigerist replied. “Now when in history was perfect security achieved? You can’t reach the entire human race, you know. You may broadcast ‘Love thy neighbor’ while flooding the planet with inducer waves. But what of the guy who doesn’t tune you in? Suppose he happens to be reading Mein Kampf instead? Or is down in a mine or driving through a tunnel? Or simply asleep?

“Is everyone who’s to be given any knowledge of the inducer’s existence . . . will everybody be dragooned first into a mental Janissary corps? I don’t see how that can be practical. Their very presence and behavior would tip off shrewd men. And then there are ways . . . burglary, assassination, duplication of research . . . And once the fact is loose—”

Pidge had to stand a minute and fight his nerves after he stepped out of the car. What if something went wrong?

The suburban street (trees, hedges, lawns, flowers, big well-built houses, under afternoon sunlight that brought forth an odor of growth and a chorus of birdsong) pressed him with its alienness. He was from the inner city, tenements, dark little stores, bars and poolhalls that smelled of urine, smog and blowing trash and thundering trucks and gray crowds. This place was too goddamn quiet. Nobody around except a couple of kids playing in a yard, a starchy nurse pushing a stroller down the sidewalk, a dog or two.

Pidge squared his narrow shoulders. Don’t crawfish now! After the casing you’ve done, the money you’ve laid out—He rallied resentment. You’re not doing a thing except claiming your share. The rich bitches have pushed you around too goddamn long.

And he wasn’t drawing any attention here. He was sure he wasn’t. White, and small, not like those bastards who’d shoved him out of their way through his whole life, oh, he’d show them how brains counted . . . Shave, haircut, good suit, conservative tie, shined shoes, Homburg hat (the wires and transistors beneath his wig enclosed his scalp like claws), briefcase from the Goodwill and car borrowed but you couldn’t tell that by looking. And he’d spent many hours in this neighborhood, watched, eased into conversation with servants; everything was known, everything planned, he’d only to go through with his program.

And They wouldn’t appreciate his backing out. He’d had a tough time as was, wheedling till They let him in on the operation—the set of operations—he’d gotten wind of. Buying in had cost him all he could scrape together and a third of the haul when he was finished. And it had demanded he do his own legwork and prove he had a good plan.

Well, sure, they’d had plenty of trouble, expense, and risk beforehand, to make these jobs possible. Finding out what was being done in the jails that turned so many guys into squares, hell, into stoolies; finding guards who could be bought; arranging for an apparatus to be smuggled out and stuff to be left behind so the fuzz would think it’d simply been busted; getting those scientific guys to copy the apparatus. And of course it couldn’t be used more than for maybe a week, on the scale that they intended. Though people were awful stodgy, unalert, these days—those that watched the speeches on TV or read the papers; don’t ever do that, Pidge—the cops wouldn’t be too dumb to understand what had happened. Then the apparatus wouldn’t be good for anything but hit-and-run stuff.

If Pidge screwed up now, they would be mad. Probably. They’d make an example of him.

He shivered. His shoes clacked on the sidewalk.

The doorbell of his target sounded faintly in his ears. He tried to wet his lips, but his tongue was too dry. The door swung noiselessly open. A maid said, “Yes, can I help you?”

Pidge pressed the clasp of his briefcase the way he’d been taught. “I have an appointment with Mr. Ames,” he said.

For an instant she hesitated. His heart stumbled. He knew the reason for her surprise; he’d studied this layout plenty close. The industrialist always spent Wednesdays at home, seeing no one except people he liked. He could afford to.

The maid’s brow cleared. “Please come in, sir.”

After that, it was a piece of cake. Ames got on the phone and managed to arrange the withdrawal of almost two million in bills, certified checks, and bearer bonds without causing suspicion. He thought Pidge was giving him a chance to make a killing. His wife and staff made no fuss about waiting in an offside room, when Pidge whispered to them that national security was involved.

Naturally, the Brink’s truck took a couple of hours to arrive. Pidge had himself a bonus meanwhile. Ames’ daughter came back from high school, and she was a looker. Not expert in bed, you couldn’t expect that of a virgin, but he sure made her anxious to please him. Pidge had never had a looker before. He was tempted to bring her along. But no, too risky. With his kind of money he’d be able to have whatever he wanted. He would.

After the armored truck was gone and the haul had been transferred in suitcases to Pidge’s car, he told the people of the house that life was worthless and an hour from now they should let Ames shoot them. Then the man should do himself in. Pidge drove off to his rendezvous with Their representative, who held his ticket and passport.

“Oh, you can raise assorted horrors,” Fenner argued, “but to be alive is to take chances, and I don’t see any risks here that can’t be handled. I mean, the United States Government isn’t a bloc, it’s composed of people, mostly intelligent and well-meaning. Their viewpoints vary. They’re quite able to anticipate a possible monolith and take precautions.”

“Tell me, what is a monolith?” Sigerist retorted. “Where does rehabilitation leave off and brainwashing begin? What are the constitutional rights of Birchers and militants? Of criminals, for that matter?”

“You’re right,” Mottice said. The sweat was running heavily down his face; they caught the reek of it. “This must never be used on humans without their prior consent and full understanding.”

“Not even on those who’re killing American boys and Thai peasants?” Sigerist asked. “Not even to head off nuclear war? Given such an opportunity to help, can you do nothing and live with yourself afterward? And once you’ve started, where do you stop?”

“You can’t keep the secret forever,” Duarte said. “Believe me, we’ve tried to think of ways. Every plausible consequence of the inducer’s existence that we’ve talked about involves the destruction of democracy. And none of the safety measures can work for the rest of eternity. The world has more governments, more societies than ours. Maybe you can convert their present leaders. But the fact of conversion will be noticed, the leaders will have successors, the successors could take precautions of their own and quietly instigate research.”

In his last years George Rainsdon always had a headache. He was old when the mesh was planted beneath his scalp, and the technique was new. The results were therefore none too good in his case; and the doctors said that doing the job over would likely cause further nerve damage. As a rule the pain was no worse than a background, never completely outside his awareness. Today it was bad, and he knew it would increase till he lay blind and vomiting.

“I’m going home early,” he told his secretary, and rose from the desk.

Penelope Gorman’s impeccable fagade opened to reveal sympathy. “Another sick spell?” she murmured.

Rainsdon nodded, and wished he hadn’t when the pain sloshed around his skull. “I’ll recover. The pills really do help.” He attempted to smile. “The cause is good, remember.”

Her lips tightened. “Good? Only in a way, sir. Only because of the Asians, the radicals, the criminals. Without them, we wouldn’t need protection.”

“Certainly not,” Rainsdon agreed. The indoctrination lecture, required of every citizen before implantation was performed, had made that clear. (A beautiful ceremony had evolved, too, for the younger generation: the eighteen-year-old candidates solemn in their new clothes, families and friends present, wreaths of flowers on the inducer, religious and patriotic exhortations that stirred the soul.) To be sure, crime and political deviancy were virtually extinct. Yet they could rise again. Without preventive measures, they would, and this time the inducer would let them wreck America. Eternal vigilance is the price of liberty.

Tragic, that indoctrination of the whole world had not been possible. But in the chaos that followed the Treaty of Peking, the breakup of the Communist empires after Communism was renounced . . . a Turkoman adventurer somehow welding together a kingdom in Central Asia, somehow obtaining the inducer, probably from a criminal . . . the United States too preoccupied with Latin America, with inculcating those necessary bourgeois virtues that the pseudointellectuals used to sneer at . . . and suddenly the Asians had produced nuclear weapons, insulating the helmets for everybody, their domain expanded with nightmare speed, soon they too were in space and could cover the Western Hemisphere with inducer signals, turning all men into robots unless defenses were erected, civilian as well as military—Rainsdon forced his mind out of that channel. Truth was truth; still, people did tend to get obsessed with their righteous indignation.

“You knock off too, Mrs. Gorman,” he said. “I’ve no chores for you till I recover.” The small advisory service—international investments—that he had founded after leaving a diplomatic corps that no longer needed many personnel used public data and computer lines. His office was thus essentially a one-man show.

“Thank you, sir. I appreciate your kindness. I’m snowed under by work in the Edcorps.”

“The what?” he asked, having scarcely heard through a fresh surge of migraine.

“Educational Corps. You know. Volunteers, helping poor children. The regular schools teach them to honor their country and obey the law, of course. But schooling can’t overcome the harm from generations of neglect, can’t teach them skills to make them useful and productive citizens, without extra coaching.” Mrs. Gorman rattled her speech off so fast that it must be one she often gave. Repetition didn’t seem to lessen her earnestness. Sexual sublimation? Rainsdon wondered. He’d had occasion to visit her apartment. Aside from photographs of her late husband, it might almost have been a cell in a convent.

They left together. She matched her pace to his shuffle. The elevator took them down and they emerged on Fifth Avenue. Sunlight spilled through the crisp autumn air that could blow nowhere but in New York. Pedestrians strode briskly along the sidewalks. How wise the government had been to phase out private automobiles! How wise the government was!

“Shall I see you home, Mr. Rainsdon? You look quite ill.”

“No, thank you, Mrs. Gorman. I’ll catch a bus here and—”

The words thundered forth.

PEOPLE OF AMERICA! CLAIM YOUR FREEDOM! YOUR DIABOLICAL RULERS HAVE ENSLAVED YOU WITH LIES AND SHUT YOU AWAY FROM THE TRUTH BY WIRES IN YOUR VERY BODIES. EVERYTHING YOU HAVE BEEN FORCED TO BELIEVE IS FALSE. BUT THE HOUR OF YOUR DELIVERANCE IS AT HAND. THE SCIENTISTS OF THE ASIAN UNION HAVE FOUND THE MEANS TO BREAK OPEN YOUR MENTAL PRISON. NOW HEAR THE TRUTH, AND THE TRUTH SHALL MAKE YOU FREE! HELP YOUR FRIENDS, YOUR LIBERATORS, THE FREE PEOPLE OF THE ASIAN UNION, TO DESTROY YOUR OPPRESSORS AND EXPLOITERS! RISE AGAINST THE AMERICAN DICTATORSHIP. DESTROY ITS FACTORIES, OFFICES, MILITARY FACILITIES, DESTROY THE BASIS OF ITS POWER. KILL THOSE WHO RESIST. DIE IF YOU MUST, THAT YOUR CHILDREN MAY BE FREE!

Down and down the skyscraper walls, from building after building, from end to end of the megalopolis, the voices roared. Rainsdon knew an instant when there flashed through him, Megaphone-taper units, radio triggered, my God, they must’ve planted them over the whole country, a million in New York alone, but they’re small and cheap, and somewhere beyond that bright blue sky a spacecraft is beaming— Then he knew how he had been betrayed, chained, vampirized by monsters of cynicism whose single concern was to grind down forever the aspirations of mankind, until the Great Khan had been forced to draw his flaming sword of justice.

Penny ripped apart her careful hairdo. Graying blonde tresses spilled, Medusa locks, over her breasts while she discarded gown, shoes, stockings, corset, the stifling convict uniform put on her by a gaoler civilization. Her shriek cut through the howl of the crowd in the only words of protest she knew, remembered from distant childhood. “Fuck the establishment! Freedom now!”

Rainsdon grabbed her arm. “Follow me,” he said into her ear. His headache was nearly gone in a glandular rush of excitement, his thoughts leaped, it was like being young again and leading a charge in Korea, save that today his cause was holy. “Come on.” He dragged her back inside.

She struggled. “What you at, man? Lemme go! I got pigs to kill.”

“Listen.” He gestured at the human mass which seethed and bawled outside. “You’d be trampled. That’s no army, that’s a mob. Think. If the Asians can develop an inducer pattern that gets past our mesh, be sure the kept American technicians have imagined the possibility. Maybe they’ve developed a shield against it. They’d have sat on that, hoping to keep secret—Anyway, they’ll have made preparations against our learning the truth. They’ll send in police, the Guard, tanks, helicopters, the works. And these buildings, they probably screen out radiation, they must be full of persons who haven’t had the slave conditioning broken. Penelope, our best service is to find that voice machine and guard it with our lives. Give more people a chance to come out where the truth can reach them.”

They located the device in an office and waited, deafened, tormented, stunned by its magnitude of sound. Hand in hand, they stood their prideful watch.

But no one disturbed them for the hour or two that remained, and they never felt the blast that killed them.

The Asians knew that American missile sites were insulated against any radio impulses that might be directed at the controllers. They counted on those missiles staying put. For what would be the point of an American launch, when Washington could no longer govern its own subjects? At the agreed-upon moment, their special envoy was offering the President the help of the Great Khan in restoring order; at a price to be sure.

The Great Khan’s advisors were wily men. However, being themselves conditioned, they did not realize they were fanatics; and being fanatics, they did not have the empathy to see that their opponents would necessarily resemble them.

In strike and counterstrike, the big birds flew.

“Well, that’s certainly a hairy bunch of scenarios,” Fenner admitted after a long discussion. “Are you sure things would turn out so bad?”

“The point is,” Sigerist replied, “do we dare assume they wouldn’t?”

“What do you propose, then?” Mottice asked.

“That’s what we’ve invited you here to help decide,” Duarte said.

Ginsberg shifted his bulky body. “I suspect you mean you want us to ratify a decision you’ve already made,” he said, “and its nature is obvious.”

“Suppression—No, damn it!” Fenner protested. “I admit we need to exercise caution, but suppressing data—”

“Worse than that,” Sigerist said most softly. “As the recognized authorities in your different fields, you’ll have to steer your colleagues away from this area altogether.”

“How will we do that?” Yuang demanded. “Suppose I cook an experiment. Somebody is bound to repeat it.”

“We’re big game, you know,” Mottice put in. “A new-made Ph.D. who found us out would make a name for himself. Which would reinforce him in pursuing that line of work.”

“The ways needn’t be crude,” Sigerist said. “If you simply, without any fuss, drop various projects as ‘unpromising,’ well, you’re able men who’ll get results elsewhere; you’re leaders, who set the fashion. If you scoff a bit at the concept of neuroinduction, raise an eyebrow when Rocard is mentioned . . . it can be done.”

He paused. Drawing a breath, rising to his feet, he said, “It must be done.”

Ginsberg realized what was intended and scrabbled frantically across the table at the device. Sigerist pinioned his arms. Duarte pulled an automatic from his pocket. “Stand back!” the younger man shouted. “I’m a good target shooter. Back!”

They stumbled into a comer. Ginsberg panted, Fenner cursed; Mottice glared; Yuang, after a moment, nodded. Duarte held the gun steady. Sigerist began crying. “This was our work too, you know,” he said through the tears. He pressed a button. A vacuum tube glowed and words come out of a tape recorder.

Five years afterward, Sigerist and his family tuned in a program. Most educated persons did, around the world. The Premier of the Chinese People’s Republic had announced a major speech on policy, using and celebrating the three synchronous relay satellites which his country had lately put into orbit. Simultaneous translation into many languages would be provided.

Considering the belligerence of previous statements, Sigerist joined the rest of the human race in worrying about what would be said. He, his wife, the children who were the purpose of their lives, gathered in a solemn little group before the screen. The hour in Peking was well before dawn, which assured that India was the sole major foreign country where live listening would be inconvenient. Well, the eastern Soviet Union too, not to mention China itself; but there would be rebroadcasts, printed texts, commentaries for weeks to come.

When the talk was over, Sigerist’s wife sought his arms and gasped with relief. He held her close and grinned shakily across her shoulder at the kids. The Premier’s words had been so reasonable, so unar-guably right. They had opened his eyes to any number of things which had not occurred to him before. For a moment during those revelations he’d wondered, been afraid . . . and then, actually quite early in the speech, the Premier had smiled with his unmatched kindliness and said: “The enemies of progress have accused us of brainwashing, including by electronic methods. I tell you, and you will believe me, nothing of the sort has ever happened.”